(Bass guitar)
(باس الغيتار)
(Bass guitar and accordion)
(باس الغيتار وأكورديون)
♫ You're older than you've ever been ♫
♫أنت أكبر سنا من أي وقت مضى♫
♫ and now you're even older ♫
♫والآن أنت أقدم حتى♫
♫ and now you're even older. ♫
♫والآن أنت أقدم حتى♫.
♫ You're older than you've even been ♫
♫أنت أكبر سنا من أي وقت مضى♫
♫ and now you're older still. ♫
♫والآن لا تزال أقدم ♫
♫ Time ♫
♫الوقت♫
♫ is marching on ♫
♫يمر♫
♫ and time ♫
♫والوقت ♫
♫ is still marching on. ♫
♫لا يزال يمر♫
♫ This day will soon be at an end ♫
♫هذا اليوم ستكون له نهاية قريبة♫
♫ and now it's even sooner ♫
♫والآن هي أقرب حتى♫
♫ and now it's even sooner. ♫
♫والآن هي أقرب حتى.♫
♫ This day will soon be at an end ♫
♫هذا اليوم ستكون له نهاية قريبة♫
♫ and now it's even sooner ♫
♫والآن هي أقرب حتى♫
♫ and now it's sooner still. ♫
♫وهي لا تزال قريبا الآن.♫
♫ You're older than you've ever been ♫
♫أنت أكبر سنا من أي وقت مضى♫
♫ and now you're even older ♫
♫والآن أنت أقدم حتى♫
♫ and now you're even older. ♫
♫والآن أنت أقدم حتى.♫
♫ You're older than you've ever been ♫
♫أنت أكبر سنا من أي وقت مضى♫
♫ and now you're even older ♫
♫والآن أنت أقدم حتى♫
♫ and now you're older still. ♫
♫والآن لا تزال أقدم.♫
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
Good morning everybody.
صباح الخير للجميع.
We are They Might Be Giants.
نحن "ذي مايت بي جاينتس".
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I am wearing the Al Gore in-ear monitors
ألبس شاشات آل غور الأذنية
he wore on the Larry King show
التي ارتداها في برنامج لاري كينغ
and I'm hearing that transmission and not mine.
وأنا أسمع ذلك البث وليس البث الخاص بي.
But I guess that's in keeping,
لكنني أفترض أن ذلك في البقاء،
so now we'll just move to the PowerPoint presentation,
حسنا سنقوم الآن بالانتقال إلى عرض الباور بوينت،
ladies and gentlemen.
سيداتي سادتي.
This is a brand new song.
هذه أغنية جديدة.
In the spirit of TED, we're bringing you something
في روح تيد، أحضرنا لكم شيئا
that has not been released.
لم يتم إصداره بعد.
John, do you want to introduce the song?
جون، هل تريد التقديم للأغنية؟
This is a song about a creature called a hummingbird moth
هذه الأغنية حول مخلوق يدعى فراشة الطائر الطنان
which imitates another creature
والتي تقلد مخلوقا آخر
which imitates yet another creature.
والذي يقلد مخلوقا آخر.
It's completely fucked up
الأمر مختل تماما
and can only be explained in song.
ويمكن أن يشرح فقط في أغنية.
♫ Everyone is crying at the dread hypnotic flying ♫
♫ الجميع يبكي على الطيران المرعب التنويمي♫
♫ of the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫للنحلة للطائر للفراشة.♫
♫ You can't walk, you can't ramble ♫
♫لا تستطيع المشي، لا تستطيع التنزه♫
♫ 'cause you're gonna have to scramble ♫
♫لأنه سيكون عليك الزحف♫
♫ from the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫من نحلة طائر الفراشة.♫
♫ Catbird is a cat ♫
♫الكتبرد هو قط♫
♫ but he's got bugness in his veins. ♫
♫لكن لديه حشرية في عروقه.♫
♫ Manhouse lives within himself ♫
♫بيت الرجل يعيش في ذاته♫
♫ with thoughtful human brains. ♫
♫بأدمغة بشرية عميقة.♫
♫ Neither one is equal ♫
♫ولا واحدة منها مساوية♫
♫ to the challenge of the freak we'll call ♫
♫لتحدي الغريب الذي سنتصل به♫
♫ the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫نحلة طير الفراشة.♫
♫ Now the moth ♫
♫الآن الفراشة♫
♫ defeats the mouse and man. ♫
♫تهزم الفأر والإنسان.♫
♫ It's messing with the plan. ♫
♫إنها تعبث بالخطة.♫
♫ It can't be believed ♫
♫لا يمكن أن تصدق♫
♫ 'cause it's just a hummingbird moth ♫
♫ لأنها فقط فراشة طائر طنان♫
♫ who's acting like the bird ♫
♫التي تتصرف مثل الطائر♫
♫ that thinks it's a bee. ♫
♫التي تعتقد أنها نحلة.♫
♫ Got a brand new shipment ♫
♫لديها شحنة جديدة ♫
♫ of electrical equipment ♫
♫من المعدات الكهربائية♫
♫ it's addressed to the bottom of the sea. ♫
♫إنها معنونة لعمق المحيط.♫
♫ Send a tangerine-colored ♫
♫أرسل غواصة نووية ♫
♫ nuclear submarine ♫
♫ملونة باليوسفي♫
♫ with a sticker that says STP. ♫
♫بملصق يقول STP.♫
♫ Windshield wiper washer fluid ♫
♫سائل غسيل زجاج السيارة الأمامي♫
♫ spraying in the air ... ♫
♫يرش في الهواء ...♫
♫ headlights under head lice ♫
♫المصابيح الأمامية تحت قمل الرأس♫
♫ under hats lie everywhere. ♫
♫تحت القبعة ينتشر في كل مكان.♫
♫ Subatomic waves ♫
♫موجات ذرية♫
♫ to the underwater caves ♫
♫للكهوف التحت مائية♫
♫ of the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫لنحل طائر الفراشة.♫
♫ Now the moth defeats the mouse and man. ♫
♫الآن الفراشة تهزم الفأر والإنسان. ♫
♫ It's messing with the plan. ♫
♫إنها تعبث بالخطة.♫
♫ It can't be believed ♫
♫لا يمكن تصديقها♫
♫ 'cause it's just a hummingbird moth ♫
♫لأنها مجرد فراشة طائر طنان♫
♫ who's acting like a bird ♫
♫والتي تتصرف كطائر♫
♫ that thinks it's a bee. ♫
♫يعتقدد أنه نحلة.♫
♫ Is it us or is this messed up? ♫
♫هل يتعلق الأمر بنا أم أن هذا عبث به؟♫
♫ Everyone's deforming ♫
♫الجميع يتشوه♫
♫ in the presence of the swarming ♫
♫في ظل ازدحام♫
♫ of the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫نحلة طائر الفراشة.♫
♫ Protozoa, snakes and horses ♫
♫طفيليات، وأفاع، وأحصنة♫
♫ have enlisted in the forces ♫
♫موجودة في قوى♫
♫ of the bee of bird of the moth. ♫
♫نحلة طائر الفراشة.♫
♫ Catbug is a cat ♫
♫الكاتبغ هو قط♫
♫ but he's got bugness in his veins. ♫
♫لكن لديه حشرية في عروقه.♫
♫ Manhouse lives within himself ♫
♫بيت الرجل يعيش في ذاته♫
♫ with thoughtful human brains. ♫
♫بأدمغة بشرية عميقة.♫
♫ Neither one is equal ♫
♫ولا واحدة منها مساوية♫
♫ to the challenge of the freak we'll call ♫
♫لتحدي الغريب الذي سنتصل به♫
♫ the bee of the bird of the moth. ♫
♫نحلة طير الفراشة.♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks a lot.
شكرا جزيلا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
So we are past our 1,000th show.
إذن فنحن تجاوزنا عرضنا الآلف.
Probably somewhere around 1,500.
ربما في مكان ما حول 1500.
It's hard to know.
من الصعب أن أعرف.
We've only done two shows in 2007 so far,
أدينا عرضين فقط لحد الآن سنة 2007،
but our first show
لكن عرضنا الأول
was actually the coldest performance we've ever had.
كان في الواقع أبرد أداء عرفناه قط.
It was 19 degrees in St. Louis about a month ago
كانت 19 درجة في سانت لويس قبل حوالي الشهر
and I'm happy to report
وأنا سعيد لإبلاغكم
that this performance you are seeing today
أن هذا الأداء الذي ترونه اليوم
is the earliest we have ever performed.
هو أكثر أداء مبكر أديناه.
So thank you.
لذا شكرا لكم.
We are cultural test pilots, ladies and gentlemen.
نحن طياروا اختبار ثقافيين، سيداتي سادتي.
How early can a rock performance begin?
كيف يمكن أن يبدأ أداء روك مبكرا؟
Not all the facts are in about performing
ليست هناك كل الحقائق حول الأداء
at 8.30 in the morning.
في 8.30 صباحا.
I can tell you the 19 degree thing
أستطيع إخباركم أن مسألة ال19 درجة
was fantastic.
كانت رائعة.
All right.
حسنا.
So we don't know that much
إذن لا نعرف بذلك القدر
about the history of violinists
بخصوص تاريخ عازفي الكمان
but we do know that when we entered
لكننا نعرف أنه حين ندخل
the state of New Jersey
ولاية نيوجرسي
there is an uptick in violence.
هناك تنام في العنف.
This song is called "Asbury Park."
هذه الأغنية تسمى "منتزه أزبوري."
It's based on a real life experience.
إنه مستوحى من تجربة واقعية.
♫ I ♫
♫أنا ♫
♫ I got ♫
♫ قد♫
♫ I got kicked ♫
♫قد تم ضربي♫
♫ I got kicked in the head ♫
♫قد تم ضربي في الرأس♫
♫ backstage at the Stone. ♫
♫وراء الكواليس في حجر.♫
♫ Stone Pone. ♫
♫حجر المهر.♫
♫ I got kicked in the head ♫
♫قد تم ضربي في الرأس♫
♫ backstage at the Stone Pony ♫
♫وراء الكواليس في حجر المهر♫
♫ where I swore to the guy ♫
♫حيث أقسمت للشخص♫
♫ that the guy who took his beer wasn't me. ♫
♫أن الشخص الذي أخذ جعته لم يكن أنا.♫
♫ Me got ♫
♫أن قد تم ♫
♫ Me got kicked ♫
♫قد تم ضربي♫
♫ Me got kicked in the head ♫
♫قد تم ضربي في الرأس♫
♫ backstage at the Stone. ♫
♫وراء الكواليس في حجر ♫
♫ Stone Pone. ♫
♫حجر المهر♫
♫ Me got kicked in the head ♫
♫قد تم ضربي في الرأس♫
♫ backstage at the Stone Pony ♫
♫وراء الكواليس في حجر المهر♫
♫ where I swore to the guy ♫
♫حيث أقسمت للشخص♫
♫ that the guy who took his beer ♫
♫أن الشخص الذي أخذ جعته♫
♫ was a guy dressed like me. ♫
♫كان شخصا يلبس مثلي.♫
♫ Not me! ♫
♫ليس أنا!♫
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
Marty Beller on the drums over there.
مارتي بيلار على الطبل هناك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We want to get in as many songs as possible
نريد أن نتطرق إلى أكثر عدد ممكن من الأغاني
during our brief time here
خلال وقتنا القصير هنا
so this is the one to play.
حسنا هذا ما سيتم عزفه.
This song is called "Fingertips."
الأغنية تدعى "أطراف الأصابع."
♫ Everything is catching on fire ♫
♫الجميع يحترق♫
♫ Yes, everything is catching on fire ♫
♫نعم كل شيء يحترق♫
♫ Yes, everything is catching on fire. ♫
♫نعم كل شيء يحترق,♫
♫ Fingertips ♫
♫أطراف الأصابع♫
♫ I hear the wind blow ♫
♫أسمع هبوب الرياح ♫
♫ It seems to say ♫
♫يبدو أنها تقول♫
♫ Hello ♫
♫مرحبا♫
♫ I'm the one who loves you so. ♫
♫أنا الذي يحبك جدا. ♫
♫ Hey, now everybody, now. ♫
♫مهلا، الآن جميعا الآن. ♫
♫ Hey, now everybody ♫
♫مهلا، الآن جميعا. ♫
♫ Hey, now everybody, now ♫
♫مهلا، الآن جميعكم الآن. ♫
♫ Who's that standing ♫
♫من هذا الواقف♫
♫ at the window?♫
♫قرب النافذة؟♫
♫ I found a new friend ♫
♫وجدت صديقا جديدا♫
♫ underneath my pillow. ♫
♫تحت وسادتي.♫
♫ Come on and wreck my car ♫
♫تعال ودمر سيارتي♫
♫ Aren't you the guy who hit me in the eye? ♫
♫ألست الشخص الذي ضربني في العين؟♫
♫ Please pass the milk, please. ♫
♫من فضلك مرر الحليب، أرجوك.♫
♫ Leave me alone, leave me alone. ♫
♫دعني وحيدا، دعني وحيدا.♫
♫ Who's knocking on the wall? ♫
♫من الذي يطرق الجدار؟♫
♫ All alone, all alone. ♫
♫وحيدا تماما، وحيدا تماما.♫
♫ All by myself. ♫
♫وحيدا مع نفسي.♫
♫ What's that blue thing doing here? ♫
♫ما الذي يفعله ذلك الشيئ الأزرق هنا؟♫
♫ Something grabbed ahold of my hand ♫
♫شيء ما أمسك بقبضة يدي♫
♫ I didn't know what had my hand ♫
♫لم أعرف ما الذي أمسك بيدي♫
♫ but that's when all my troubles began. ♫
♫لكن ذلك عندما بدأت كل مشاكلنا. ♫
♫ I don't understand you ♫
♫لا أفهمك♫
♫ I cannot understand you ♫
♫لا أستطيع فهمك♫
♫ I don't understand the things you say ♫
♫لا أفهم ما تقوله♫
♫ I can't understand a single word ♫
♫ لا أستطيع فهم كلمة واحدة♫
♫ I don't understand you ♫
♫لا أفهمك♫
♫ I just don't understand you ♫
♫أنا فقط لا أفهمك♫
♫ I turn around ♫
♫نظرت حولي♫
♫ See the sound ♫
♫رأيت الصوت♫
♫ Turn around and see the thing ♫
♫نظرت حولي ورأيت الشيء♫
♫ that made the sound. ♫
♫الذي أصدر الصوت.♫
♫ Mysterious whisper ♫
♫همس غامض♫
♫ The day that love came to play. ♫
♫في اليوم الذي ظهر فيه الحب.♫
♫ I'm having a heart attack ♫
♫أنا أتعرض لنوبة قلبية♫
♫ I'm having a ... ♫
♫أنا أتعرض ل ..♫
♫ Fingertips ♫
♫أطراف الأصابع♫
♫ I walk along darkened corridors ♫
♫أمشي على طول ممرات مظلمة♫
♫ And I walk along darkened corridors ♫
♫وأمشي على طول ممرات مظلمة♫
Thank you very much -- "Fingertips."
شكرا جزيلا لكم -- "أطراف الأصابع."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
♫ We're taking calls -- from the dead. ♫
♫نحن نتلقى اتصالات -- من الموتى.♫
♫ We're taking phone calls from the dead. ♫
♫نحن نتلقى اتصالات هاتفية -- من الموتى♫
♫ They're calling from beyond the grave. ♫
♫إنهم يتصلون من وراء القبر.♫
♫ Beyond the grave. ♫
♫وراء القبر.♫
♫ They have some questions ♫
♫لديهم بعض الأسئلة.♫
♫ And things to share ♫
♫وأمور لمشاركتها♫
♫ From underneath the cold, cold ground. ♫
♫من تحت الأرض الباردة.♫
We're soliciting phone calls from dead people
نحن نلتمس اتصالات هاتفية من أشخاص موتى
as a special TED presentation.
كعرض تيد خاص.
We're taking calls live on stage
نحن نتلقى اتصالات مباشرة على الخشبة
here at TED in Monterey.
هنا في تيد في مونتيري.
And I think we have a caller coming in here.
وأظن أنه لدينا متصل جاء إلى هنا.
Hello there.
مرحبا بك.
You're live.
أنت حي.
Hello. Who's there, please?
مرحبا. من هناك من فضلك؟
Am I on the air?
هل أنا على الهواء؟
Hi there.
مرحبا بك.
You're on with They Might Be Giants.
أنت على الهواء مع "ذي مايت بي جاينتس".
This is Eleanor Roosevelt.
هذا إليانور روزفلت.
Hello, Eleanor, please ...
مرحبا، إليانور، من فضلك..
I want to talk to ...
أريد التحدث إلى ..
Please turn off your radio, Eleanor.
أرجوك أطفئ مذياعك، يا إليانور.
I wanna talk to Randi.
أريد الحديث إلى راندي.
I've got a question for Randi.
لدي سؤال لراندي.
What's your question, please?
ما هو سؤالك من فضلك؟
I want to talk to the Amazing Randi.
أريد الحديث إلى راندي المذهل.
Do you have a laminated badge, Eleanor?
هل لديك شارة مغلفة يا إليانور؟
I want my million dollars.
أريد المليون دولار خاصتي.
Eleanor, I'm sorry,
إليانور، أنا آسف،
do you have a laminated badge?
هل لديك شارة مغلفة؟
No, I don't have a badge.
لا، ليست لدي شارة.
Well, I think we're going to stop
حسنا، أظننا سنوقف
that part of the show.
ذلك الجزء من البرنامج.
Here's a song we like to think of
ها هي أغنية نود النظر إليها
as the future anthem of TED.
على أنها النشيد الوطني المستقبلي لتيد.
It's actually a children's song
إنها في الواقع أغنية أطفال
but like so many projects for children
لكن مثل الكثير من مشاريع الأطفال
it's really just a Trojan horse
إنها ليست سوى حصان طروادة
for adult work.
لأعمال البالغين.
This song is called
هذه الأغنية تدعى
"The Alphabet ...
"أبجدية ..
Of Nations!"
الأمم!"
♫ Algeria, Bulgaria, Cambodia, Dominica, ♫
♫الجزائر، بلغاريا، كمبوديا، دومينيكا، ♫
♫ Egypt, France, The Gambia ♫
♫مصر، فرنسا، غامبيا ♫
♫ Hungary, Iran, Japan, Kazakhstan, ♫
♫هنغاريا، إيران، اليابان، كازاخستان،♫
♫ Libya and Mongolia. ♫
♫ليبيا ومنغوليا.♫
♫ Norway, Oman, Pakistan, ♫
♫النرويج، عمان، باكستان،♫
♫ Qatar, Russia, Suriname, ♫
♫قطر، روسيا، سورينام،♫
♫ Turkey, Uruguay, Vietnam, ♫
♫تركيا، أوروغواي، فييتنام،♫
♫ West Xylophone, Yemen, Zimbabwe. ♫
♫غرب الاكسليفون، اليمن، زيمبابوي.♫
♫ Algeria, Bulgaria, Cambodia, Dominica, ♫
♫الجزائر، بلغاريا، كمبوديا، دومينيكا، ♫
♫ Egypt, France, The Gambia, ♫
♫مصر، فرنسا، غامبيا ♫
♫ Hungary, Iran, Japan, Kazakhstan, ♫
♫هنغاريا، إيران، اليابان، كازاخستان،♫
♫ Libya and Mongolia. ♫
♫ليبيا ومنغوليا.♫
♫ Norway, Oman, Pakistan, ♫
♫النرويج، عمان، باكستان،♫
♫ Qatar, Russia, Suriname, ♫
♫قطر، روسيا، سورينام،♫
♫ Turkey, Uruguay, Vietnam, ♫
♫تركيا، أوروغواي، فييتنام،♫
♫ West Xylophone, Yemen, Zimbabwe. ♫
♫غرب الاكسليفون، اليمن، زيمبابوي.♫
♫ Azerbaijan, Bolivia, Canada, ♫
♫أذربيجان، بوليفيا، كندا،♫
♫ Australia, Belgium, Chad, ♫
♫أستراليا، بلجيكا، تشاد،♫
♫ Afghanistan, Brunei, China, Denmark, ♫
♫أفغانستان، بروناي، الصين، الدانمارك،♫
♫ Ecuador, Fiji, Guatemala, ♫
♫الإكوادور، فيجي، غواتيمالا،♫
♫ Algeria, Bulgaria, Cambodia, Dominica, ♫
♫الجزائر، بلغاريا، كمبوديا، دومينيكا، ♫
♫ Egypt, France, The Gambia, ♫
♫مصر، فرنسا، غامبيا ♫
♫ Hungary, Iran, Japan, Kazakhstan, ♫
♫هنغاريا، إيران، اليابان، كازاخستان،♫
♫ Libya and Mongolia. ♫
♫ليبيا ومنغوليا.♫
♫ Norway, Oman, Pakistan, ♫
♫النرويج، عمان، باكستان،♫
♫ Qatar, Russia, Suriname, ♫
♫قطر، روسيا، سورينام،♫
♫ Turkey, Uruguay, Vietnam, ♫
♫تركيا، أوروغواي، فييتنام،♫
♫ West Xylophone, Yemen, Zimbabwe. ♫
♫غرب الاكسليفون، اليمن، زيمبابوي.♫
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
You've been a wonderful 8:30 audience.
لقد كنتم جمهور 8:30 رائعا.
Have a great session.
أتمنى لكم جلسة رائعة.
Thank you all.
شكرا لكم جميعا.